she has sippy she received a bachelor's
in science in material science and
engineering from my key followed by
masters of engineering in biomedical
engineering from MIT and then when to
use in San Diego for a PhD in
publications and
thank you thank you dr. Ortiz well so
I've come here from across campus from
the Department of kinesiology
Andy Galvan dr. Galpin here is the
faculty I work with and we brought a
bunch of the kinesiology students along
with us and we're here to talk to
biological science department today as
the nature of the research we do is at
this very unique interface between
exercise physiology and biochemistry so
one of the main interests in our lab is
studying human performance so what and
we do this at a molecular and cellular
level and sort of the question is what
are some of these proteins and gene
signals that are transpiring to lead to
the adaptations that are going on at
elite levels of performance elite
athletes and this is a really
interesting question kind of in a
biological science sense that most of
the time we apply our study of biology
to the study of disease when we're
looking at health which of course is
very necessary but a lot of times we
ignore the physiology of people at the
opposite end of the health spectrum so
people who are doing really really well
in something and are pushing the
boundaries of human physiology human
performance and you know we we don't
really have a full concept of what
health is if we ignore at that end of
the spectrum and there could be a lot of
interesting things we learn from
studying these people that could indeed
help other people with disease later
down the line we're really just
motivated by curiosity at this point
okay well what is what is it that allows
us to study real live human athletes
well the fact is that we are focused on
skeletal muscle tissue and this is one
of the few tissues from humans that we
can actually biopsy
and how people come into the lab willing
consenting participants and we can
extract some of their tissue we
primarily focus on this muscle here on
the it's on the outside of your
quadricep called the vastus lateralis
probably 80 to 90 percent of muscle
biopsy research is focused on this
particular muscle it's very large it's
very well exposed easy to reach not a
whole lot of arteries going through it
stuff you could mess up and it was also
very reflective of the type of training
you do and your exercise habits
lifestyle in general so we use this
specialized biopsy needle andy has been
trained to do he does all the biopsies
we do in our lab it is kind of a legit
surgical technique but it is quite quick
only about a second or so and we're able
to take out muscle tissue 100 milligrams
at most it's quite small about the size
of the pencil head eraser but now we can
section off the tissue into these little
bundles some people say they look like
tuna steak tartare and then we kind of
pickle those bundles for a week or so
and then we're able to pick through them
and isolate out single muscle fibers so
this is another really unique aspect
from studying muscle is that the fibers
are in a sense single cells themselves
probably the only cell in your body that
you can actually see with your naked eye
that's pretty incredible as well another
unique property about them is that they
have tons of my own nuclei so we're
taught most cells have only one nucleus
you know the control center but muscle
cells are very unique in this aspect is
that they are dotted with my own nuclei
all across the spectrum of the fiber and
the fiber I mean these are only segments
that we've cut out of here but a fiber
could theoretically stretch the entire
length of your thigh so we can image the
fibers which we've done in the past
we can also dissolve them we can lyse
the fibers and look at the proteins that
are inside of them the proteins that are
being expressed and the proteins that
may be activated towards stimuli such as
exercise so this still is an amazing
thing to me that we are able to do live
in vivo human research this is kind of a
very rare opportunity all the research I
did you know standard biochemistry
research I did in my PhD is all focused
on you know either a cell culture or
maybe mice or rats and there's all sorts
of really cool interesting stuff so you
can do with those systems but at the end
of the day sometimes you're always
asking yourself hmm
does this really relate to humans does
this really translate to what's going on
in my body and in this case we can say
yes all right so another thing we're
very focused on in our lab is something
called fiber type so this is defined by
a protein called myosin heavy chain or
MHC which is a very important protein in
your muscle that is essentially this
molecular motor that is responsible for
all of the contractions that you do and
through time you move any part of your
body and this myosin heavy chain is
known to exist in three protein versions
or isoforms that are encoded by in the
human genome there is the slow twitch
MHC one the fast twitch isoform to a and
an ultra-fast ultra-fast which isoform
called MHC 2 X so these three different
protein isoforms a cell can express any
number of combinations of these
particular proteins and so this de leads
to what we call fiber types that
describe the cells themselves which
there are six known fiber types found in
humans there are three that contain just
a pure single isoform both for one 2a
and also 2x and then there are hybrid
fiber types some that it will express
one and two a or two a 2x
then another hybrid type that will
express all three of them now these MHC
isoforms are so named based on their
actual properties the speed at which
they are performing their motor
reactions and so that actually translate
into the properties of the muscle fiber
the cell itself in that we see
increasing contractile power the more
fast which isoforms are expressed and
we've sort of listed them out here and
another thing about human muscle is that
we have a mixture of different fiber
types in basically all of our muscles so
it will be this heterogeneous population
where we'll have a slow twitch fiber
next to a fast twitch fiber next to a
hybrid and there's some fiber types that
will be more prevalent than others so
these four here are generally the most
common ones we find in young healthy
adults whereas the two these two types
are a bit more rare particularly the
pure form of MHC 2 X so how do we run
our fiber typing procedures well
probably one of the main experimental
outputs of our lab are these very large
high-throughput big gel sds-page
electrophoresis so we have the capacity
to run eight big gels at a time and each
of them can be loaded with 26 fibers so
we can type 208 individual muscle fibers
to determine their identities and
generally we take about a hundred per
participant and we run them overnight
and then like a typical SDS page you get
separation of the proteins based on size
so the MHC one slow-twitch isoform is
smaller so it runs down further than the
fast-twitch isoforms and we stain for
them using a silver stain because
there's so much MHC protein in your
muscle cells that you can actually see
it with the silver stain instead of a
Western blot and then we go through each
lane of the gel which is
a single fiber and look at the bands and
identify the fiber type this gel is a
little bit rarer because we found a lot
of the triple hybrid here but
essentially to show those different
bands resolving alright so fiber type I
mentioned that it's a composition in
each individual but the actual
composition can vary and is highly
dependent on the type of exercise and
training that you do so we typically
represent it here as percentages so
somebody could be 45% slow-twitch mhc1
30% fast which and then a certain
proportion of the hybrid fiber types and
are trying to visualize how this works
with different types of activities
people might do our collaborator at San
Francisco dr. Jimmy Bagley prepared this
figure to sort of conceptualize that so
on the x-axis he plots the ratio of slow
twitch fibres to fast twitch fibres and
slow twitch fibers are they're actually
a lot more adapted towards endurance
types of exercise so they typically have
a lot more mitochondria they're able to
sustain an activity for a long period of
time but a lower intensity type of
activity whereas the fast twitch fibers
are more adapted towards power and speed
strength types of exercises where you're
exerting a lot of force in a short
amount of time
high intensity but it starts to lose its
its capacity typically these fibers have
a lot of glycogen content in them which
depletes pretty quickly now here on the
y-axis Jimmy's put hybrids so percentage
of hybrids over pure fibers here we have
less hybrids versus more hybrids which
actually tend to reflect how sedentary
or how active you are so now he went
through a bunch of literature studies
where people had looked at different
populations of athletes and people and
what they do
and we see some things that start to
make sense so long-distance runners
endurance athletes are down at this
corner where they have a lot of slow
twitch fibers but they're quite well
trained so they're down here on the
hybrids whereas competitive sprinters
have to do really high-intensity work in
a short period of time they have a lot
more fast twitch fibers but are also
well trained so down here on this axis
and then some people who are more
sedentary or just recreationally active
maybe they fall in the middle of the
spectrum here but then higher on the
hybrids axis so a lot of these
populations have been looked at but some
rather unique sports have not and one
group Olympic weightlifters we currently
have a study going on in our lab where
we took advantage of a very unique
opportunity last month there was the
World Championships of Olympic
weightlifting as well as national
championships held right here in Anaheim
and we were able to recruit through the
efforts of Andy and grad student Nate
who's been working on this project very
very extensively a bunch of of these
Olympic athletes or look during athletes
the top ones in the US of their rates of
vision classes and we're going to look
at their fiber type we think it could be
very interesting it may indeed fall down
in this side of the spectrum another
thing we're studying which is rather
unique and I'll get to later on in the
talk is we're studying both male and
female athletes which could be another
interesting dimension to see if that has
a effect from sex okay so to further
drive in this point about how fiber type
is very dependent on exercise history
perhaps even more than genetics was
another study that came through our lab
former grad student works on her thesis
with a pair of 52 year old twins so
after several decades they
differentiated
selves one had done a lot of marathons a
lot of Ironman triathletes put in a tons
and tons of mileage and the other one
for the most part was sedentary so we
called trained twin and untrained twin
and so we took biopsies from them and
then looked at this is in a sense as the
fiber of majah Nets so a bunch of muscle
fibers mixed together and we're just
looking at the proportion of the actual
proteins expressed but even with that
we're seeing a very very significant
difference between these two individuals
who have the exact same DNA the exact
same genetics the trains when is over
90% slow-twitch MHC one where the
untrained twin has more significant
proportions of the fast which forms and
presumably and a lot of hybrid types and
also I'll be talking about this protein
later ampk we found gene expression to
also be very significantly varied
between these two individuals so really
driving in the point that fiber type
which was previously thought to be
determined by your genetics is probably
a lot more determined by what you do
okay and finally we've got this other
very new project that just started I
said we didn't stay at study disease but
we have some new collaborators from
Stanford who do and they look at
end-stage renal disease so patients who
they're pretty old 65 to 80 years old
and they are on hemodialysis some of
them had obesity and diabetes that led
to the kidney failure others are very
frail but they're all having in addition
to the kidney failure their muscles are
starting to atrophy to waste away and so
they took muscle biopsies and we're very
interested in what the fiber type of
these individuals might be and so we
picked apart some of the samples the
fibers were a little bit harder frail
ERDs that come between but we got some
initial preliminary results that are
quite interesting so we'll go through
and
type this gel here the six fiber types
again we see a number of the slow-twitch
and HC ones which we always do but then
and of course some hybrids as we'd
expect but then this this fiber type
that I told you is quite rare the pure
MHC 2x we appear to be getting several
of those as well and we can identify it
because the band here I know they're
kind of faint but it's resolving with
the top bands of the two a 2x hybrid and
then even weirder was this fiber sample
so I said there were these that exist
this looks like a 1 2 X hybrid to me
because you got a one down here and then
a band up at the top this fiber type is
thought not to exist so we had another
biopsy sample that we went through and
again saw two a two x's and more of the
pure two x's we're starting to be
convinced there they're a triple hybrid
here and then some fast which here but
then I know it's faint but this looks
like another one 2x this is pretty crazy
maybe we do have a seventh fiber type
here and so we could probably think
about what's going on here it seems
strange that these patients would have
these very weird fiber types really
really fast twitch and their theories
about it it's almost as if so the muscle
is wasting away and the few fibers you
have remaining are trying to do whatever
they can to keep some level of function
to be able to get you out of bed and so
maybe that's what they do they
differentiate into this super fast ultra
fast fiber type to be able to do that or
maybe they just have no clue what
they're doing so they're making
something really weird like this alright
so I'm gonna switch gears a little bit
now and talk about protein kinase is in
cell signaling which we'll all rap into
in a bit but any rate you might have
heard of cases I've studied them a lot
in my PhD work they are very key parts
of cellular signaling processes and what
they are is an enzyme that trans
a phosphate off of ATP and puts it on
another protein and this often works as
an on-off switch for that particular
protein substrate which is the target of
the kinase kinase is will also be
substrates for other kinase 'iz and this
often turns them on so that they can
process the signaling event or turns
them off in some cases as well so we're
interested in kinase is because they're
very important to physiological
processes they will take an input such
as a hormone or exercise in our case and
produce various outcomes that all lead
to performance related aspects all right
so if you had to choose a kinase out
there that was the most tied to exercise
that there is it would probably be this
one AMPK and it is this master regulator
of cellular energy homeostasis so it has
been repeatedly shown to be activated by
exercise it's a very hot kinase to study
even has its own conferences devoted
entirely to it but how it works is
pretty cool it is this hetero trimer
what we call so it is a complex of
actually three different proteins
encoded by three different genes but
they all need to come together in order
to work and the subunits one is a
catalytic subunit so it's responsible
for performing the chemical reaction
there's a scaffolding some a subunit
which links the protein to other
proteins or glycogen and the gamma
subunit which is the regulatory it's
kind of like the sensing subunit decides
if the kinase is going to be on or off
and what happens is when you start
exercising you start drastically
lowering your ATP in your muscle cells
and so it's getting broken down into
these components a MP and adp the single
and dye phosphate forms and these bind
to ampk on the regulatory subunit
and ultimately change the conformation
so it allows it to be more
phosphorylated itself and turned on as
an active kinase and be able to
phosphorylate other proteins now a mpk
not only does it have these three
different subunits
it also has multiple versions of those
subunits so isoforms so two versions of
alpha two versions of beta and then
three for gamma
all right so what are some of these
targets substrates and functions of AMPK
well one of the best-known substrates is
this protein called acetyl co a
carboxylase or acc so it is responsible
for synthesizing fatty acid chains well
phosphorylation by a and PK is actually
a negative regulatory site so it turns
off ACC and now instead of synthesizing
fatty acid chains you can start breaking
them down ah it has similar effects on
another khuns enzyme called glycogen
synthase we turn that off and now we can
start breaking down glycogen and then
start using these energy stores to make
more ATP rapidly that we need to keep on
living
alright and then there two other
substrates that are interesting to study
I'm not even going to read their names
because these are examples of horrible
biology nomenclature gone very bad but
at TB c1 d1 and TBC 1.d4 so these
proteins are interesting because they
linked ampk into the insulin signaling
pathway and ultimately sensitize your
muscle cells towards glucose uptake so
taking out glucose out of the
bloodstream so we can go make more ATP
ultimately and this is kind of the
explanation for this phenomenon called
the post exercise anabolic window or as
many of us like to call it the window of
games this is explaining why people like
to drink their protein and carbohydrate
shakes right after they've been
exercising and it's really because ampk
has been activated specifically in their
muscle cells where they've been working
out and has turned on these processes to
sensitize those those cells to glucose
uptake and now all of those nutrients
that they're taking in can go almost
entirely segregated to the muscle cells
and not see your fat cells during that
time so pretty cool other interests in
ampk I'll just mention it definitely has
clinical interests metformin is this
very old drug that's been used to treat
Type 2 diabetes for decades and now like
a lot of old drugs people knew that it
worked but they didn't know how that it
works or how it works and more recently
it was shown that metformin actually
activates AMPK and you think about it
that actually makes sense
because what is one of the best
treatments out there for type 2 diabetes
is exercise and what also activates
ampk is exercise another drug that was
specifically developed to activate ampk
is known as AI car and this was an
interesting example about ten years ago
ten years ago at the Salk Institute they
did a very study that got a lot of press
where they treated mice with AI car and
they found that the mice had a 49
percent increase in their endurance
capabilities from being on this drug and
here's an example of how when it
involves a performance-enhancing drug
that is probably the fastest time that
research goes from the lab to directly
towards its application because I think
I heard that it was either the summer or
so after this paper came out they
literally found AI car in the dumpsters
outside of the hotels where the ho Tour
de France athletes were saying no joke
so of course I car is now on the list of
banned substances from many competitions
all right so coming into our research
kind of now marrying these two things
I've talked about here the fiber types
and the AMPK we're really interested in
how does a and B Que behave differently
in different muscle fiber types that is
really the ultimate question so I keep
saying this term fiber type specific
what exactly does that mean why is it
important well I'll just walk you
through a kind of hypothetical analogy
to conceptualize that so we have this
mixture of different fiber types well
let's imagine for a second that the
slow-twitch fibers are marathon runners
and the fast twitch fibers are
bodybuilders this is again performance
study and imagine you have a mixed
population of these marathoners and
bodybuilders that you're studying and
maybe you're measuring something like
their time to run 10 kilometers well we
know all about the bet that these two
different groups of people are going to
perform differently on this type of test
and maybe we want to study something
conditions like nutrition effects on
their performance so whether they're
running in a fasted state or a fence
date well now if we run these studies
like the majority of muscle biopsy
research is done out there we wouldn't
actually separate them out we would just
have one group that is everybody and we
might ultimately not see any
significance between the conditions that
were measuring now what makes intuitive
sense to all of us
is that we need to measure these groups
individually to have them in two
different categories which of course we
have a very significant difference in
their performance and then here we might
actually see significance from the
effects that we're studying so this this
point I'm making is that if you go back
to the fiber types you have a very
similar situation we know that slow
twitch and fast twitch fiber types have
very different metabolic properties so
it makes total sense to separate them
out and especially if we're going to be
studying a metabolic signaling protein
to be studying it in the segregated
populations well why aren't more labs
doing that what does it come down to
well it actually comes down to the
methods so methods for fiber type
specific research ten turn out to be a
lot more time intensive a lot more
laborious and ultimately sometimes not
really feasible so I'll walk you through
that so what you have to do is you
separate out the fibers which we already
do to do fiber typing knots not a big
deal but then if we're gonna look at a
protein like ampk we have to cut them in
half one part goes for the typing the
other half we store separately for the
analysis later on and we have to wait
until we get at least 20 plus fibers of
each type we want to study and then
dissolve them all together in one pool
to make one sample that we're studying a
and PK out of and this is ultimately
because ampk is that such a much lower
level of expression compared to myosin
heavy chain and then for the less common
fiber types like these hybrids that
really just makes the study of them very
unfeasible what would be much better if
we had single fiber methods so in this
case we would just isolate the fibers
and dissolve them individually and use
the same sample for both the fiber
typing and then the signaling protein
analysis well what's stopping us from
doing the single fiber types of
techniques well we've run into this
technique called western blotting which
of course is the go-to for when you want
to analyze proteins out of cells so I
did this last year where I pulled
together a bunch of slow twitch and fast
switch to a fibers in these you know
20-plus of each of them and then also
ran a single fiber alongside of them and
looked for some of our ampk isoforms so
we're already seeing some promising
results here that the expression is very
different in some of the fiber types of
course we're getting those ugly
unpredict
frustrating Western blot effects here
but we're getting no expression no
detection at all out of the single fiber
it's just too low in protein and so
we're up against this problem how can we
lower our limit of AMPK detection and
how can we enhance the right reliability
and conserve our samples which are very
precious well
this technique Western blotting oh I'll
tell you do you know what it has in
common with a Walkman they were both
invented in 1979 and we're not walking
around with Walkmans anymore but we're
still doing Western blots you know and
I'm not the only one that's had
frustrations with his technique it is it
is quite well at widespread and
frustrations are vented through internet
memes but ultimately it was putting a
barrier on the research we wanted to do
we really needed to find a way to get
around it because we knew we were gonna
get really interesting exciting results
and so what do you do when you're up
against a problem like that well you
talk to some of your friends so a good
friend of mine who's an entrepreneur in
the biotech industry and she works at
this company called protein simple well
she told me about this very new
instrument that they've come up with
called
capillary Nano immunoassay or the
commercial term simple Western so this
sounded like a complete Fanus to be
fantasy to me when she first described
it that it's actually a machine that
automates an entire western blot assay
for you and it does that using similar
pros same principles as a Western blot
so you're essentially separating out
your proteins by size then your
immobilizing them and then you're
proving them with antibodies against
your specific target and a peroxide
substrate going through but what it does
is that it puts these separation
matrices
into individual capillaries which are
very long and narrow and are able to
concentrate your protein sample so you
can get to lower limits of detection and
then it does it automated so you
essentially just pipette this plate that
they manufacture with your samples your
primary antibodies your secondary
antibodies your substrates your wash
buffers you put the plate in the machine
you snap in a cartridge you close the
door and you press Start and it runs
automatically if you come back it takes
just under three hours you come back
later to fully analyze data it's
incredible so let's see if this can
solve our problem with the muscle fiber
detection so here we have a serial
dilution of fibers dissolved just
different fiber concentrations and now
let's look at one of our a.m. P K's beta
2 for instance so beta 2 on Western blot
we're really only detecting it at the
top three concentrations of fibers and
then the signals kind of petering out
getting lost and ugly Western blot
things are happening here's what it
looks like with the capillary assay this
is incredible this got us to nearly 20
fold lower in detection and now we can
actually study the single fiber level
range which is just really advances what
we want to do and it's got great
linearity great reproducibility
reproducibility this was a particularly
awesome antibody that had no nonspecific
targets
otherwise and the Machine ultimately
measures everything on like a
chromatogram type view where you're
quantifying the area under a curve okay
so this was figure 1 from our recent
publication just out in the Journal of
applied physiology and we were able to
in that paper show fiber type specific
ampk
so I'll just go through a couple of
those examples from the paper alpha-2 we
found to be more expressed in the fast
twitch fiber types beta 2 was equivalent
in the one in two ways but then had some
differences between the two hybrids here
the most interesting results though were
for the gamma the regulatory isoforms
where gamma two was highly expressed in
the to a fibers compared to all the rest
of them interestingly not so in the two
a 2x which again a lot of people don't
actually separate out to a and to a 2x
and this really notes how different
those fiber types are and then with
gamma 3 this one was very much expressed
in the to a to X and in fact seems to
have a profile of expression that is
almost reflects the contractile
properties of the fiber kind of
correlates directly with that which is
pretty cool and this has actually been
concurs with research from mice and rats
where they found gamma 3 more in fast
which muscles of those animals alright
so we've published that now we're
working on another project and this one
is looking at how a mpk activates in
fiber types and now we bring in
phosphorylation and the substrate
targets of our enzyme and we also bring
in exercise so this rather evil
contraption piece of lab equipment over
in kinesiology and we can look at really
interesting questions like what are some
of the metabolic effects of
high-intensity interval exercise which
seems to work in a different way than
continuous exercise also this time
period after you exercise that's when
some of the most interesting effects of
metabolism are happening and what could
be differences between the fiber types
during that period during the window of
gains all right so you a year ago I came
up with a rather intense experiment so
where we take a biopsy
rest then the subject performs six high
intensity intervals on that evil bike at
pretty close to all out for a minute and
a half then some recovery in between
another biopsied directly after the
exercise a third one thirty minutes
post exercise and then another one
ninety minutes and so you you design
something rather sadistic like this who
of course you choose as your first test
subject well this is another unique
thing about human muscle research is
that you can be your own lab rat which
is really fun I I had a great time with
this but in any case here I am in our
biopsy lab doing those bike intervals
and ultimately we're gonna look at some
of these substrates that are targeted by
AMPK which this one in particular ACCC
has almost a five pole fold
phosphorylation in response to exercise
and then of course using that beautiful
capillary athlete technique getting
beautiful figures alright so here was
some of the preliminary data from my own
fibers so just again illustrating this
point the mixed fiber model versus
single Phi or fiber type specific when
we look at mixed fibers we of course see
the increase in phosphorylation that we
expect but then in the time points
afterwards there could be a lot more
variability going on between the slow
and fast twitch fibers that were not
resolving here so now when we separate
out the fast twitch and the slow twitch
fibers we see some more interesting
effects here so at rest there's actually
already a difference in the basal
phosphorylation of a cc and then with
exercise they both go up and then come
back down at 30 minutes to a similar
degree but then the really interesting
time point here was at 90 minutes we're
in the MHC one fibers the
phosphorylation had dropped to a level
below where it had been Basel II whereas
in the
a fibers it was still maintained so the
activity was maintained so this was
really interesting of course if you're
going to publish a study like this you
need to do it in multiple subjects so
now we moved on to we've collected
tissue on six subjects so far so these
are all high intensity interval training
with these various characteristics
they're fiber type composition is
plotted here there was one guy that was
a lot more slow-twitch than the other
guys but the main thing that's the same
between all of them is that they're very
low in percentage of hybrid fiber types
which reflects their training which is
what we were interested in and then for
the time points
I decided based on my own data to
substitute out the 30-minute time point
for a hundred eighty minute time point
that I thought would be a little bit
more interesting and ultimately five
biopsies is just way too statistic way
too much for biopsies is acceptable all
right so here's some preliminary data
from three of these guys analysis of
this substrate ACC so right here we're
looking at expression gene expression of
ACC which we weren't you know this is
pretty much what we expected it does not
depend on the fiber type and doesn't
really change with exercise again this
is only three ends we're gonna get up to
nine in the end so these error bars
should shrink but now looking at the
phosphorylation of ACC this other
protein target we see again similar to
the effects that I got from my own
fibers where at this 90-minute time
point there's still an elevated signal
in the two A's and then coming back at
180 to a lower level than the ones but
again we need some more ends here the
even more interesting substrate target
was this one TBC 1.d4 and so this one
right off the bat has a very different
expression profile in the slow twitch
versus the fast twitch fibers and then
even more interesting is that the
expression in the slow twitch fibers
actually seems to respond to the
exercise where it goes down and then
comes back up after the subject has
recovered whereas in the fast twitch
fibers it doesn't really change at all
and now we look at phosphorylation of
that target and we have a much higher
level of phosphorylation in the fast
twitch fibers at basal levels than the
slow twitch and then in the fast twitch
fibers it doesn't really change
throughout the exercise but with the
slow twitch fibers it goes up and then
comes back down and this is a perfect
example whenever you're doing you know
studies on phosphorylation of proteins
you always have to divide your phospho
protein signal over your total protein
signal otherwise you could miss effects
like this if you're just normalizing it
by like a tubulin expression marker so
we're again we're gonna need to collect
more more data here but we're starting
to interpret this as in this particular
substrate TBC 1.d4 is much more relevant
to the signaling that's going on in the
slow twitch fibers and isn't really
important in the fast twitch fibers
where presumably another protein might
take that role quite likely the TB C 1 D
1 the sister protein of this one that's
in the same family all right so I've
talked a lot about how many of these
studies are almost always done with
mixed fiber samples
well another commonality between a lot
of these studies you'll see with human
muscle is this when you read the methods
you noticed I had also picked a
population of men for that study there
yes so are we really studying humans if
we're just studying men and this is
actually part of a larger problem
throughout biomedical
Sciences that a lot of labs tend to
study more male mice and rats versus
female subjects and has even been picked
up by popular media outlets and it even
comes to a more significant level when
you look at clinical trials so for
example ambien which is very popular
well-known drug for treating sleep
disorders well when it was initially
studied in clinical trials it was done
with a population of men and when it
went to market and people started using
it they found Oh women needs to take a
lower dosage oh our bad so again these
are things you really need to consider
and on our end we're really interested
in female athletes so we're living in an
era where women are going after strength
and combat sports and very high
intensity levels they're pursuing muscle
essentially they they want to be strong
it's it's it's now culture is kind of
changing and they they're representing
these really interesting research
subjects as well and how could their
physiology be working in a different way
than male physiology especially since we
know that hormones are very work hand in
hand with muscle now there was one study
that was done with ampk and women where
they looked in a population of men
versus women during submaximal exercise
and they sound found some interesting
effects here but again this was a study
with mixed fiber samples so they didn't
really know in the end if this was
really a difference between the sexes or
if maybe the women had a higher
percentage of slow-twitch fibers which
could be a very likely explanation for
this result here and also this was
submaximal exercise what if they were
all doing the high-intensity all-out
type of protocol we're using so this
would be awesome so you add a population
of women
another group to the current study that
we're running as we would be immediately
able to address questions like this well
then the real question comes down to why
aren't we studying women well a lot of
people would say off the bat oh it must
be sexism well it turns out it's not
it's because of this thing this thing
called the menstrual cycle that we all
learned about in fifth grade health
class so women have a period of roughly
28 days where they experience
fluctuation fluctuations and multiple
different hormones and are highly
variable especially two principal female
sex hormones estrogen and progesterone
that reach you know intense highs and
lows throughout the cycle and if you
look at the methods that that paper that
did ampk with women you read into them
you'll see this so all the women in that
study had a normal menstrual cycle they
weren't on any birth control and they
came in to the lab for the biopsies
between days 7 to 10 well if you've ever
run a study with human subjects before
you know that the scheduling can often
get very complicated the scheduling with
the subject the investigators human
subjects don't live in the lab you don't
have control over them and if you're
trying to do something here where women
don't even know when their periods gonna
start or end and you're trying to
coordinate that it's ultimately just a
huge nightmare and nobody wants to do it
and that's really the real reason is
that scientists like to go after the
lower hanging fruit the things that we
can study more quickly more without less
controls that are easier to publish and
of course men are the lower hanging
fruit goes without saying but we really
want to change this I mean we're already
with the study with the Olympic
weightlifters doing women and men and in
that study we're just looking at fiber
type which we don't really expect would
change with a münster
cycle we've seen see that as an
acceptable risk in terms of variability
but something like AMT K which has
actually been shown in the literature to
be activated by estrogen is a metabolic
signaling protein
there's definitely got to be you know
some hormonal influences on it this is
more of a concern in this case however
like I said we really really want that
that population added in there and I'm
actually thinking now that I'm going to
go towards more specific sub population
on women who are on a specific type of
birth control alright so starting to tie
all of this in where do we really want
to go here and as I mentioned at the
beginning of the talk we really want to
study elite athletes and it's something
that our lab is very uniquely in the
position to do based on all of Andy's
connections to various coaches various
athletes and understanding some of these
properties especially these newer
athletes these days who are now
combining strength power speed endurance
all of these physical capabilities
together in one package which was
previously thought in her field not to
really be possible either you could be
really strong or you could have a lot of
endurance but now they're kind of
setting a new bar on that and again what
could be some of the differences between
men and women and how they adapt that
training what different types of
training might work better for them and
that types of in those types of
situations and again this is a huge
question but we think fibertite has
definitely got to play a big role in
this in this answering this question and
also being able to look at how metabolic
properties differ between fiber types so
maybe we might even get switching of
these properties at these elite levels
of performance
so with that I'll finish acknowledgments
of course dr. Randy Galton who I joined
his lab about a year and a half ago and
it's been an incredible experience he
runs an amazing lab
some amazing opportunities for students
in kinesiology and biological sciences
we love it when people have biochemistry
experience but we can also teach
everybody everything they need to know
Cara
Lazar Ska's is the graduate student
working on this project and she is in
fact an MMA fighter herself so brings
this rather unique skill from from that
and has this insane mental toughness to
weather all of the things that the
punches that graduate school throws at
you
Nate Serrano he's our other grad student
who's in charge of that whole Olympic
weightlifter study and then Jose and
Ryan who were graduated students last
year who helped me with this project we
have a lot of other undergrads who help
us out and then dr. Lea Brown former
director of the Center for sport
performance our collaborator in San
Francisco and Tim Geiger from protein
simple and with that I'll move on to
questions I also have my contact info
here again Andy and I are always
interested in giving people research lab
experiences and with that we'll take
questions
[Applause]
well that would certainly be very
interesting but the ethical limitations
of that you have to be 18 in order to
give informed consent so yes what for
the biopsy oh yeah yeah yeah there's
other things we could do with
adolescence but not the types of things
I'm talking about here yes
yeah yeah that that could could
certainly be a case there I mean your
fiber type there have been some studies
that show it can change within a process
of two weeks even it's it's very
adaptable and it's again yet presumably
more when you're younger it's got to be
changing a lot more rapidly
uh yeah with the with the men we're
running in our current study we have
been taking some very tight controls on
them know who drinking that actually
usually the hardest one is that they
have to abstain from exercise for like
48 hours before the study some of these
guys are like oh my god how could I not
train but yes we keep a log of
everything they've eaten in the past
week generally they're all you know it's
it's more just we don't want any extreme
types of diets where they're not eating
any hardware hydrates or any fats or
something like that so that's a great
question you've you've raised actually
the most of the studies that are done
with women out there for muscle biopsies
are very often with postmenopausal women
because it gets rid of the whole
hormonal variability problem and of
course there are a lot of globs that are
focused on aging of muscle because
that's a huge problem and so there's
often a lot more funding to go after
studies with aging populations but
essentially at that point it's
interpreted that okay you flatlined on
your hormones it's not going to change
maybe you're more like how the men are
but of course the men like testosterone
also varies a lot but we kind of just
ignore that
sure
I was wondering if you like what how how
people's history in terms of like how
much they exercise like a child yeah
yeah that's something I don't think that
really has been looked at but again it's
usually we evaluate people based on the
past few years of their training and
kind of what they had settled into those
types of habits but no I mean you know
our subjects could be have wildly
different childhoods we haven't exactly
asked about that we asked about like
major diseases or accidents or
hospitalizations and things like that
but you know I mean that the the main
idea is that we're all a very malleable
system like muscle is one of these few
tissues in your body that you have some
amount of freewill over like if you want
to make more muscle fibers or Yamano
make them work better you have kind of
an idea how to do that either you know
if I'd like to grow more brain cells I'm
not exactly sure how to go about that
but yeah again you can you can change
you can make up for poor decisions in
your past for sure
mm-hmm yeah yeah that's a great question
there are most other muscles that are
biopsied especially the soleus which is
known to have more slow twitch fibers
again it is still a mixture it's very
different in humans than it is with mice
and rats other species where in mice the
soleus is almost entirely all slow
twitch fibers so you can just take
tissue out of that and basically say
this is slow twitch fiber and then some
of the other muscles are all fast twitch
fiber but yeah humans soleus is
definitely a higher percentage of slow
twitch we also do gastrocnemius learning
these terms I not an exercise
physiologist and that one I think has a
little bit more fast twitch again
they're both in the calf there's other
muscles studied and again it's it's
always a composition with humans I mean
across no it's more it's more oriented
around specific muscles that they're
they're utilizing in whatever type of
activity they're doing and of course
with the Olympic weightlifters that's
awesome for us because that is like one
of their main workhorses for that type
of activity
potentially we have to confirm that sure
sure
so hybrid fibers I will point out to
start with they have been a lot more
ignored in our field than the pure forms
sometimes they're a little bit harder to
distinguish but the method we run with
the sds-page shells not using any
antibodies or anything or
immunohistochemistry that is like the
surest way to pinpoint the hybrids but
the hybrids again it's there's different
you know theories behind this one of
them may ultimately be that when you're
not giving muscle training stimulus a
kind of incentive to differentiate one
way or the other towards endurance or
towards power and speed the muscle the
fibers don't really know what to do so
they're kind of in this nebulous state
of one or the other that's one theory of
course but you know again a lot of these
things a lot of these theories or dogmas
kind of get reworked as the field
advances and especially we haven't
studied much with women before does the
hybrid sort of sedentary versus trained
you know does that work with them as
well or could it be very different and
they're different hybrid types sometimes
we think the one to a maybe found more
entrained people we've seen that or is
maybe the two a to X is more a marker of
being sedentary
so yeah the hybrids are still a huge
open area of Investigation
yes that would be awesome if we find the
right Kabul operations um there are
actually some papers out there that are
starting to do proteomics and mass spec
out of single fibers and I'm sure you
could get the methods going for looking
at RNA PCR again RNA is a molecule that
you can replicate more of so you can
make more of it so you can actually
study it protein you're kind of stuck
with what you're got there but yeah that
would definitely be a really cool thing
to do and just you know RNA in
particular I mean we've been all focused
on protein here but RNA is very
interesting in terms of at the genetics
in terms of the things we're studying
these training populations what might
the RNA like total expression profile
look like you know in those heat maps
looking at all these different genes be
in like an elite athlete population
versus other populations of people
you
[Applause]